

# João Pedro Dias

#### ENGINEER, DEVELOPER, RESEARCHER, AMATEUR PHOTOGRAPHER,

Porto, Portugal

☑ jpmdias@fe.up.pt | 脅 jpdias.me | ☑ jpdias | 勵 joaopdias | Ў jpd1as | ὧ jpdias

## Summary.

Current Researcher at INESC TEC and pursuing a PhD degree in Informatics Engineering. Graduated from the Integrated Masters in Informatics and Computing Engineering, I'm passionate about technology, with a special focus on security and privacy, web development, data mining & Internet of Things. Besides that, I'm also an amateur photographer, football player, book lover and science addict. **ORCID**: 0000-0001-9066-6436

### **Education**

#### **Doctoral Program in Informatics Engineering - ProDEI (PhD)**

Porto, Portugal

FACULTY OF ENGINEERING OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PORTO (FEUP)

2016-Exp. 2020

· Work under Supervision of Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD and Co-Supervision of João Pascoal Faria, PhD

#### Master in Informatics and Computing Engineering - MIEIC (MSc)

Porto, Portugal

FACULTY OF ENGINEERING OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PORTO (FEUP)

2011-2016

- GPA: 15 out of 20
- Volunteer at Semana Profissão: Engenheiro (SPE) 2014 & 2016

#### **Sciences and Technologies**

Amarante, Porto, Portugal

2008-2011

• GPA: 17 out of 20

## **Work Experience**

## Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto

Campus FEUP, Porto, Portugal

INVITED ASSISTANT PROFESSOR

Fev. 2017 - Today

 $\bullet \ \ \text{Teaching practical lectures of Operating Systems and Software Development Laboratories}.$ 

# INESC TEC – Institute for Systems and Computer Engineering, Technology and Science | CSIG – Centre for Information Systems and Computer Graphics

Campus FEUP, Porto, Portugal

RESEARCHER

May 2017 – Today

- Researching in the area of Internet of Things, with special focus on Blockchain and Healthcare applications, in the scope of the project NanoSTIMA: Macro-to-Nano Human Sensing: Towards Integrated Multimodal Health Monitoring and Analytics.
- Project details: nanostima.inesctec.pt

#### **LIACC – Artificial Intelligence and Computer Science Laboratory**

University of Porto, Porto, Portugal

RESEARCHER

Sept. 2016 - Apr. 2017

- Researching data representation and data mining applications on railway transportation systems in the scope of the project PEDDIR: Weigth in Motion and Wheels Defect Detection.
- Technologies: MongoDB, Python and Web Development | Project details: www.peddir.eu & www.in2rail.eu

ShiftForward, S.A. Porto, Portugal

SUMMER ENGINEERING INTERN

Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2015

- Development of a Deploy Logger Service, a service for documenting and recording the release of new product versions over time.
- Technologies: Scala and Backbone.js | Project details: shiftforward.github.io/malamute

#### Centro Hospitalar do Tâmega e Sousa, E.P.E.

Penafiel, Porto, Portugal

IT DEPARTMENT INTERNSHIP

Jul. 2014 - Aug. 2014

- Development of an expedient management system for replacing the existent system based on paper archives.
- Technologies: MySQL and PHP

## **Teaching**

#### INTEGRATED MASTER IN INFORMATICS AND COMPUTING ENGINEERING · FEUP · 5 YEARS

2018 - 2019 Invited Assistant Professor, Software Development Laboratory · 4<sup>th</sup> year (First Semester)

- 3 hours per week

2018 - 2019 *Invited Assistant Professor*, **Operating Systems** · 2<sup>nd</sup> year (Second Semester)

– 4 hours *per* week

2017 - 2018 Invited Assistant Professor, Operating Systems · 2<sup>nd</sup> year (Second Semester)

- 4 hours per week · 2 classes · 45 students

### **Publications**

### CONFERENCE ARTICLES (PEER-REVIEWED)

#### **BLOCKCHAIN-BASED PKI FOR CROWDSOURCED IOT SENSOR INFORMATION**

Porto, Portugal

Guilherme Pinto, João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2018

14<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Information Assurance and Security { DOI: To Appear }

#### A BLOCKCHAIN-BASED SCHEME FOR ACCESS CONTROL IN E-HEALTH SCENARIOS

Porto, Portugal

João Pedro Dias, Hugo Sereno Ferreira and Ângelo Martins

2018

14<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Information Assurance and Security { DOI: To Appear }

#### **DYNAMIC ALLOCATION OF SERVERLESS FUNCTIONS IN IOT ENVIRONMENTS**

Bucharest, Romania

Duarte Pinto, João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2018

16<sup>th</sup> IEEE International Conference on Embedded and Ubiquitous Computing { DOI: 10.1109/EUC.2018.00008 }

## A REACTIVE AND MODEL-BASED APPROACH FOR DEVELOPING INTERNET-OF-THINGS SYSTEMS

Coimbra, Portugal

João Pedro Dias, João Pascoal Faria and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2018

7<sup>th</sup> Software Engineering Doctoral Symposium (SEDES 2018) – Part of the 11th International Conference on the Quality of Information and Communications Technology (QUATIC'2018) { DOI: 10.1109/QUATIC.2018.00049 }

#### A Brief Overview of Existing Tools for Testing the Internet-of-Things

Västerås, Sweden

João Pedro Dias, Flávio Couto, Ana C.R. Paiva, Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2018

First International Workshop on Verification and Validation of Internet of Things (VVIoT 2018) – Part of the 11<sup>th</sup> IEEE Conference on Software Testing, Validation and Verification (ICST 2018) { DOI: 10.1109/ICSTW.2018.00035 }

#### **PATTERNS FOR THINGS THAT FAIL**

Vancouver, Canada

António Ramadas, Gil Domingues, João Pedro Dias, Ademar Aguiar, Hugo Sereno Ferreira 24<sup>th</sup> Conference on Pattern Languages of Programs (PLoP 2017) { DOI: To Appear } {PDF}

2017

# TOWARDS A FRAMEWORK FOR AGENT-BASED SIMULATION OF USER BEHAVIOUR IN E-COMMERCE CONTEXT

Porto, Portugal

Duarte Duarte, João Pedro Dias, Hugo Sereno Ferreira and Zaf. Kokkinogenis

 $15^{th}\ International\ Conference\ on\ Practical\ Applications\ of\ Agents\ and\ Multi-Agent\ Systems\ (PAAMS'17)\ \{\ DOI:\ PAAMS'17\}$ 

10.1007/978-3-319-61578-3\_3}

## AUTOMATING THE EXTRACTION OF STATIC CONTENT AND DYNAMIC BEHAVIOUR FROM F-COMMERCE WERSITES

Madeira, Portugal

João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira

2017

8<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Ambient Systems, Networks and Technologies (ANT'17) { DOI: 10.1016/j.procs.2017.05.355 }

#### A HANDS-ON APPROACH ON BOTNETS FOR BEHAVIOR EXPLORATION

Porto, Portugal

João Pedro Dias, José Pedro Pinto and José Magalhães Cruz

2017

2<sup>nd</sup> International Conference on Internet of Things, Big Data and Security (IoTBDS 2017) { DOI: 10.5220/0006392404630469 }

#### **INFORMAL PUBLICATIONS & OTHERS**

#### A PRELIMINARY STUDY ON MESH NETWORKS AND IOT

Porto, Portugal

FILIPA BARROS, LUIS SOUSA, JOÃO PEDRO DIAS AND HUGO SERENO FERREIRA 11<sup>th</sup> Meeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2018)

2018

## **AUTOMATING THE EXTRACTION OF STATIC CONTENT AND DYNAMIC BEHAVIOUR FROM** Porto, Portugal **E-COMMERCE WEBSITES** João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira 2017 10<sup>th</sup> Meeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2017) A HANDS-ON APPROACH ON BOTNETS FOR A LEARNING PURPOSE Porto, Portugal João Pedro Dias, José Pedro Pinto and José Magalhães Cruz 9<sup>th</sup> Meeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2016) DISSERTATIONS REVERSE ENGINEERING STATIC CONTENT AND DYNAMIC BEHAVIOUR OF E-COMMERCE Porto, Portugal SITES FOR FUN AND PROFIT SUPERVISED BY HUGO SERENO FERREIRA | GRADE OF 17 OUT OF 20. 2016 Master's Dissertation, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto { ID: 10216/85374 } **Conference Organization** 2018 **Student Volunteer**, XP 2018 – 19<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Agile Software Porto, Portugal 2018 **Conference Organization Chair**, DSIE'18 – 13<sup>th</sup> Doctoral Symposium in Informatics Porto, Portugal Engineering 2018 Advisor Board Member, Talk a Bit – Student Organized Techn Conference, 6<sup>th</sup> Edition Porto, Portugal 2017 **Student Volunteer (Media Coverage)**, EPIA 2017 – 18<sup>th</sup> EPIA Conference on Artificial Porto, Portugal Intelligence 2017 **Web Communication Co-chair**, ACM CarSys 2017 – The Second ACM International Utah, USA Workshop on Smart, Autonomous, and Connected Vehicular Systems and Services, part of the The 23<sup>rd</sup> Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking (MobiCom 2017) 2017 **Advisor Board Member**, Talk a Bit – Student Organized Tech Conference, 5<sup>th</sup> Edition Porto, Portugal 2016 **Conference Chair**, Talk a Bit – Student Organized Tech Conference, 4<sup>th</sup> Edition (2016) Porto, Portugal 2016 **Web Communication Co-chair**, 2016 IEEE 19th International Conference on Intelligent Rio de Janeiro, Brazil Transportation Systems (ITSC 2016) 2014 **Student Volunteer**, Inter-University Programming Marathon (MIUP 2014) Porto, Portugal 2014 **Student Volunteer**, INForum - Symposion on Informatics (INForum 2014) Porto, Portugal **Educational & Scientific Activities** MASTER'S DISSERTATION CO-SUPERVISING

2017	Dynamic Allocation of Serverless Functions in IoT Environments by Duarte	Porto, Portugal
- 2018	Pinto, Supervised by Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD, Masters in Informatics and	
	Computing Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto { ID: 10216/114149 }	
2017	BLOCKCHAIN AS A PKI FOR OWNERSHIP CONTROL OF IOT DEVICES by Guilherme Pinto,	Porto, Portugal
- 2018	Supervised by Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD, Masters in Informatics and Computing	
2010	Engineering, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto { ID: 10216/114144 }	
2016	Interoperability In Software Applications For Smart Cities: Towards A	Porto, Portugal
- 2017	REFERENCE ARCHITECTURE by José Pedro Pinto, Supervised by Rosaldo Rossetti,	
	PhD, Masters in Informatics and Computing Engineering, Faculty of Engineering,	
	University of Porto { ID: 10216/107529 }	

#### **PROGRAM COMMITTEES & REVIEWS**

2017	Program Committee (Senior) Member, Talk A Bit – Student Organized Tech	Porto, Portugal
	Conference, 7 <sup>th</sup> Edition (2019)	
2017	Program Committee Member, IEEE S3C 2017 - 2017 IEEE Summer School on Smart	Natal, Brazil
	Cities	
2017	IEEE Intelligent Vehicles Symposium (IEEE IV'17), Reviewer	California, USA
2017	IEEE 20th International Conference on Intelligent Transportation Systems (IEEE	Yokohama, Japan
	ITSC 2017), Reviewer	

## **Invited Talks & Workshops**

#### Information Systems and Software Engineering Seminars (SESI & SES)

Lisboa, Portugal

HOSTED AT FACULTY OF ENGINEERING, UNIVERSITY OF PORTO FOR STUDENTS OF THE MIEIC & MESW DEGREES

Sept. 2017

• **Seminar**: How to Kill Your Privacy and IoT Your Home Along the Way.

Pixels Camp 2017 Lisboa, Portugal

HOSTED BY BRIGHT PIXEL AND BETA-I

Sept. 2017

• Workshop: PiHeadquarters or How to Take Control of your House with Raspberry Pi and Docker.

#### OPOSEC Meetup: [0x33] - The Meet

Porto, Portugal

HOSTED BY BLIP.PT

Apr. 2016

• **Presentation**: A hands-on approach on botnets for a learning purpose.

**Share World Seminar 2015** – "Europe vs. Asia: Grass Is Always Greener On The Other Side"

FEUP, Porto, Portugal

HOSTED BY SHARE GLOBAL STUDENT THINK TANK

March 2015

• Workshop: How To Create Your First Personal Webpage.

## **Additional Training**

2018	1st UPTEC School on the Future of Computing, UPTEC – Science and Technology Park	FBAUP, Porto, Portugal
	of University of Porto	
2017	CyberTalk: Security - Business Enablement, Multicert - Electronic Certification	FEUP, Porto, Portugal
	Services, S.A.	
2017	Project Management, ERASMUS+ Mobility for teaching	FEUP, Porto, Portugal
2016	AWS Technical Essentials Online, Amazon Web Services – Training and Certification	Online
2015	Practical Workshop in Agile Project Management, Strongstep - Innovation in	UPTEC, Porto, Portugal
	Software Quality	
2015	CERN Spring Campus, CERN - European Organization for Nuclear Research	Lisbon, Portugal
2014	M101JS: MongoDB for Node.js Developers, MongoDB University	Online

## Skills & Languages \_\_\_\_\_

Programming	Python = • Node.JS = • C/C++ = • Scala = • Java = • C# = • PHP =	
<b>Web Technologies</b>	$HTML5 \equiv \bullet CSS \equiv \bullet JavaScript \equiv \bullet Laravel(PHP) \equiv \bullet Flask(Python) \equiv \bullet Bootstrap(CSS) \equiv \bullet jQuery(JS) \equiv $	
Databases	MySQL = • PostgreSQL = • InfluxDB = • MongoDB =	
Others	Arduino ≡• Git ≡• Android ≡• Windows Apps ≡• Docker ≡• LaTeX ≡	
Languages	Portuguese (Mother-tongue) <b>=</b> • English <b>=</b>	

## Pro Bono Activity \_\_\_\_\_

#### **ACADEMIC**

#### **IEEE University of Porto Student Branch**

Porto, Portugal

STUDENT MEMBER

2012 – Todav

**EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE (SECRETARY)** 

2013 - 2015

- As a voluntary member I had organized and co-organized some workshops (C#, Photography, ETpX, Web Development) and other events including IEEE Day, IEEEXtreme and IEEEmadC.
- As secretary I was also responsable for mantain the minutes of all meetings and other paperwork.

#### **HUMANITARIAN**

#### Luz da Vida Youth Group

Amarante, Porto, Portugal

FOUNDER MEMBER 2009 – 2011

• Founder and former active member, I had taken part of large number of activities on behalf of the village community.

### Honors & Awards \_\_\_\_\_

#### INTERNATIONAL

2017	<b>427</b> <sup>th</sup> (of 3350), IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 11.0, <i>ieee.org/xtreme</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2017	847 <sup>th</sup> (of 2815), Google Hash Code 2017, hashcode.withgoogle.com	Online – Porto, Portugal
2015	<b>189<sup>th</sup> (of 2477)</b> , IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 9.0, <i>ieee.org/xtreme</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2014	<b>Honorable Mention</b> , IEEEmadC – Mobile Application Dev. Contest, <i>ieeemadc.org</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2013	<b>126<sup>th</sup> (of 2570)</b> , IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 7.0, <i>ieee.org/xtreme</i>	Online – Porto, Portugal
2013	2 <sup>nd</sup> Place, European BEST Engineering Competition, <i>ebec.best.eu.org</i>	Warsaw, Poland

#### **DOMESTIC**

2018	<b>6<sup>th</sup> (of 31 Participants)</b> , CIBER PERSEU 2018 Portguese Army Exercise – Capture The	Portuguese Military Academy,
	Flag component by diateam, exercito.pt	Lisbon, Portugal
2011	1 <sup>st</sup> Place, PmatE Mat12 – Mathematics Competition, <i>pmate.ua.pt</i>	University of Aveiro, Portugal
2009	<b>2<sup>nd</sup> Place</b> , PmatE Fis12 – Physics Competition, <i>pmate.ua.pt</i>	University of Aveiro, Portugal

## Interests & Hobbies \_\_\_\_\_

Football Player

GRUPO DESPORTIVO E RECREATIVO DE TRAVANCA

F.A.D.A. Amateur League

2016 - 2017

#### **Amateur Photographer**

NATURE, LANDSCAPE, URBAN EXPLORATION, EVENTS

Anywhere

- 2018 Finalist at the Norte Multimédia Contest Photography Category
  Promoted by the Norte Portugal Regional Coordination and Development Commission (CCDR-N)
- 2018 Finalist at the PORTUGAL NUM ISQUEIRO BIC® Contest Promoted by the I Love My BIC initiative by BIC Portugal
- 2010 Exposition at Movimento d'Artes, Travanca, Amarante, Portugal Promoted by the Cooperativa Cultural Vinha das Artes

2008 – Today